Riccardo FINOTELLO

in riccardofinotello S riccardofinotello C thesfinox S thesfinox.github.io

Personal Data

Place of birth: Torino, Italy Date of birth: July, 13th 1993 Citizenship: Italian

Work address: Commissariat à l'Energie Atomique et aux énergies alternatives,

DES/ISAS/DPC/SEARS/LANIE, Bât. 467 p. 104,

F-91191 Gif sur Yvette CEDEX,

France

Research interests: machine learning, artificial intelligence, data science, spectroscopy, chemometrics, algebraic

geometry, string theory, conformal field theory

Description: I am currently involved in applications of AI to experimental data, specifically for spectroscopy

and chemometrics, where the possibility of applying data-driven learning models may lead to improvements in quantification and detection. I am also interested in applications of AI methods for the resolution of mathematical problems, where I contribute by introducing models inspired by advancements in computer vision and natural language processing. I studied viable methods for the computation of phenomenological amplitudes in string theory to which I contributed with the analysis of particle physics scenarios and to the study of

cosmological backgrounds.

Personal website: https://thesfinox.github.io

Work Experience

02/2021 – present: **Post-doctoral Researcher**

Commissariat à l'Energie Atomique et aux énergies alternatives, Saclay, France

Description: joint post-doc (PTC) with the *Direction des énergies* (DES/ISAS/DPC/SEARS/LANIE) and the *Direction de la recherche technologique* (DRT/LIST/DIASI/SIALV/LVML).

10/2017 - 12/2020: **Ph.D. Graduate Researcher**

Università degli Studi di Torino, Italy

Description: research in theoretical physics (string theory) and Al applications.

10/2017 – 10/2020: Scientific Associate Researcher

I.N.F.N. (National Institute for Nuclear Physics), Torino, Italy

Description: scientific association as Ph.D. student.

10/2018 - 07/2020: **Teaching Assistant**

Università degli Studi di Torino, Italy

Description: tutorship and exercise sessions for students of the B.Sc. in Physics.

Education

10/2017 – 12/2020 Ph.D. Fellow in Physics and Astrophysics

Università degli Studi di Torino, Italy

Advisor: Igor Pesando

Thesis: D-branes and Deep Learning: Theoretical and Computational Aspects In String Theory

Defended: December, 18th 2020

10/2015 - 10/2017: M.Sc. in Physics

Università degli Studi di Torino, Italy Curriculum: theoretical physics

Dissertation: Standard Model-like Scenarios in String Theory: Non Abelian D-brane Rotations and

the Classical Bosonic String

Final grade: 110/110 cum laude

10/2012 - 07/2015: **B.Sc. in Physics**

Università degli Studi di Torino, Italy

Dissertation: Perturbative Analysis: Resurgent Transeries and Hyperasymptotics

Final grade: 110/110 cum laude

Visits, Training and Internships

12/2018 Winter school and research visit

Location: Galileo Galilei Institute for Theoretical Physics (Arcetri, Firenze, Italy)

12/2017 - 01/2018 Winter schools and research visit

Location: Galileo Galilei Institute for Theoretical Physics (Arcetri, Firenze, Italy)

01/2017 - 10/2017: I.N.F.N. training for the M.Sc. degree

Location: National Institute for Nuclear Physics (I.N.F.N., Torino, Italy)

04/2015 - 06/2015: I.N.F.N. training for the B.Sc. degree

Location: National Institute for Nuclear Physics (I.N.F.N., Torino, Italy)

Fellowships, Grants and Distinctions

2020: grant as teaching assistant of the *Università degli Studi di Torino* (6 months, from 01/2020)

2019: student elected in the *Department Council* as Ph.D. representative 2018: student elected in the *Department Council* as Ph.D. representative

2017: Ph.D. scholarship assigned by the *Università degli Studi di Torino* (3 years, from 10/2017)

Teaching Experience and Outreach Activity

01/2020 - 07/2020: **Teaching Assistant in Physics**

Grant: Università degli Studi di Torino
Course: Physics 1 (1st year B.Sc. in Physics)
Competences: tutorials and exercise sessions

01/2019 - 07/2019: Teaching Assistant in Physics

Course: Waves, Fluids and Thermodynamics (1st year B.Sc. in Physics)

Competences: tutorials and exercise sessions

11/2015: **Teaching Staff**

Course: Physics at LHC (outreach project for high school students)
Funds: Piedmont regional grant for Italian scientific schools
Competences: lectures and exercises on high energy physics (in English)

Coursework and Certifications

12/2020: Reinforcement Learning

University of Alberta (via Coursera.org — credential ID: X6QTKFZDEGB2)

Fundamentals of Reinforcement Learning (credential ID: SA4PFAGGR6B5)

Sample-based Learning Methods (credential ID: KCPZAVVUT98A)

Prediction and Control with Function Approximation

A Complete Reinforcement Learning System (Capstone) (credential ID: C5JFZB5AGF4C)

10/2020: Data Science Specialisation

John Hopkins University (via Coursera.org — credential ID: QDGGFSKG8VVS)

(credential ID: J6VC2AZMGGUG) The Data Scientist's Toolbox R Programming (credential ID: 8D7TP7FHQWK2) Getting and Cleaning Data (credential ID: E3KT2J9HPKGR) Exploratory Data Analysis (credential ID: 3GYQ9UQQS3JX) Reproducible Research (credential ID: 84LX7JZYKR9W) Statistical Inference (credential ID: 2CSSYG79AQ2W) Regression Models (credential ID: YGGYSZZXM46R) Practical Machine Learning (credential ID: J9MXMYRQ47ZD) (credential ID: 2CEYYPDYG7PB) Developing Data Products (credential ID: SCJFP5JM34HR) Data Science Capstone

06/2020: Al for Medicine

deeplearning.ai (via Coursera.org — credential ID: ZXW8Y3UU4UCY)

Al for Medical Diagnosis (credential ID: GPNE8X3862JX)
Al for Medical Prognosis (credential ID: 8NPQDS4UFMJF)
Al for Medical Treatment (credential ID: 52YHADQMZCM8)

05/2020: **Deep Learning**

deeplearning.ai (via Coursera.org — credential ID: N2FWFZ9W42V2)

Neural Networks and Deep Learning (credential ID: XFKPYRXVVEKN)

Improving Deep Neural Networks: Hyperparameter tuning, (credential ID: ED599JTBLVX2)

Regularization and Optimization

Structuring Machine Learning Projects (credential ID: 8KXABGGZWRER)

Convolutional Neural Networks (credential ID: 2ZBR9Q9JLVAL)

Sequence Models (credential ID: LP9WPTVB4KV3)

04/2020: Machine Learning

University of Standford (via Coursera.org — credential ID: SDLSE9NP4XMH)

IT Skills

Programming languages: Python, R, C++, PHP, Javascript, ROOT, Matlab/Octave, Maxima, Wolfram

Mathematica, Java

Markup and scripting languages: bash, HTML, Markdown, RMarkdown

Operating Systems and Distributions: Arch Linux (main distribution), Ubuntu, Debian, CentOS, Microsoft Windows

Shell: bash, zsh, PowerShell

Modules and libraries: Scipy ecosystem, Scikit-learn, Scikit-optimize, Tensorflow (Keras), PyTorch,

LightGBM, XGBoost, Tidyr, Caret, Leaflet, Plotly, GMP, MPFR

Frameworks: Jupyter Lab and Notebook, RStudio, wxMaxima, Mathematica for scientific pro-

gramming; VIM (with plugins), Spyder for software developments; Git for version

control; GitBook for documentation

System Administration: personal instance of Nextcloud on a Raspberry Pi server (Raspbian OS), admin-

istration and web design of the journal club webpage (https://torinophd.ddns.net/) on a Raspberry Pi Apache+PHP+MariaDB installation (GitHub)

Other certifications: ECDL Core Full (European Computer Driving Licence, 04/2012)

Talks and Posters

2021: Algebraic geometry and computer vision: inception neural network for Calabi-Yau manifolds

Seminar — Data, Numbers, and Geometry - DANGER - 2021 (video conference)

Computer Vision and Algebraic Geometry: Al for Theoretical Physics

Poster — IDAI 2021 (video conference)

Intelligenza Artificiale tra Geometria e Fisica (Artificial Intelligence between Geometry and Physics)

Seminar — Escuela Alessandro Manzoni, Buenos Aires, Argentina (video conference)

An AI Perspective on Phenomenology and Strings

Seminar — Commissariat à l'Energie Atomique et aux énergies alternatives, Saclay, France (video conference)

2020: Time Dependent Defect CFT and Excited Spin Fields

Poster — Cortona Young (video conference)

2019: Spin Fields as Point-like Defects on the Worldsheet

Poster — Università Federico II, Napoli, Italy

Exploring Particle Physics in 2D BCFT: D-branes, Twist Fields and Defect CFT

Talk (Ph.D midterm seminar) — Università degli Studi di Torino, Italy

Schools and Workshops

Courses and lectures can be found at the corresponding web page

07/2021: INRIA-DFKI European Summer School on Artificial Intelligence

Online event — https://idessai.inria.fr

03/2019: String Theory from a Worldsheet Perspective

Firenze, Italy — https://www.ggi.infn.it/showevent.pl?id=289

12/2018: LACES 2018 – Lezioni Avanzate di Campi e Stringhe

Firenze, Italy — http://laces.web.cern.ch/laces/LACES18/index18.html

01/2018: GGI Lectures on the Theory of Fundamental Interactions

Fireze, Italy — http://webtheory.sns.it/ggilectures2018/

12/2017: LACES 2017 - Lezioni Avanzate di Campi e Stringhe

 $\label{lambda} Firenze, \ Italy - \verb|http://laces.web.cern.ch/laces/LACES17/index17.html| \\$

Language Skills

Italian: native speaker

English: proficient user — certifications: Cambridge FCE (pass with A), EFCELT at European level C2 French: beginner-intermediate level (can communicate professional results both orally and written)

Personal Interests

- Diploma in musical theory and melodic dictation (*Diploma di Solfeggio e Teoria Musicale*), and diploma in complementary piano studies (*Diploma di Pianoforte Complementare*) for violin
- 10 years experience as basketball player and 2 years experience as basketball coach for youth teams
- Blood donor for the AVIS (Italian Association of Volunteer Blood Donors)

Publications

Author profiles:

 $\begin{array}{ll} \text{ArXiv ID:} & \text{finotello_r_1} \\ \text{InSpireHEP:} & \text{R.Finotello.1} \end{array}$

OrcID: 0000-0002-8472-9004 ResearchGate: Riccardo Finotello2

List of publications (authors are in alphabetical order):

Preprints: H. Erbin, R. Finotello, R. Schneider, M. Tamaazousti, Deep multi-task mining Calabi-Yau four-

folds, arXiv:2108.02221.

Published: H. Erbin, R. Finotello, Inception neural network for complete intersection Calabi-Yau 3-folds,

Mach. Learn. Sci. Tech. 2 (2021) 2, 02LT03.

H. Erbin, R. Finotello, Machine learning for complete intersection Calabi-Yau: a methodological

study, Phys. Rev. D 103 (2021) 12, 126014.

R. Finotello, I. Pesando, 2D fermion on the strip with boundary defects as a CFT with excited

spin fields, Nucl. Phys. B 969 (2021) 115464.

A. Arduino, R. Finotello, I. Pesando, On the origin of divergences in time-dependent orbifolds,

Eur. Phys. J. C 80 (2020) 5, 476.

R. Finotello, I. Pesando, The classical solution for the bosonic string in the presence of three

D-branes rotated by arbitrary SO(4) elements, Nucl. Phys. B 941 (2019), 158–194.

 $Personal \ notes \ on \ various \ subjects \ (mostly \ hand \ written) \ available \ at \ https://github.com/thesfinox/personal-notes.$